[Music]
it has been estimated that 90 million
americans approximately 30 percent of
the us population currently suffers from
bad breath on a regular basis and for
those of you think phew i'm glad i'm not
one of those
it is believed that people with bad
breath can't actually smell the odor
coming out of their own mouth maybe this
is because they're used to it or it's
because when you sniff your breathing
air from below rather than in front
where you're exhaling either way the
mouth air of chronic mall load or
sufferers is tainted with compounds such
as hydrogen sulfide which produce a
stream of foul air that can be gravely
offensive to the people in their
vicinity
the characteristic smells in halitosis
include compounds that smell like feces
like skatole
the rotten egg gas hydrogen sulfide a
corpse like aroma from
cadaverine a sweaty feet compound
putrescine for the smell of decaying
meat
rotten cabbage rotten fish pee
apples don't sound so bad and i don't
even know what squashed bed bugs smell
like but the major compounds that
contribute to oral mall loader are the
vscs the volatile sulfur compounds such
as hydrogen sulfide
bacteria in our mouth predominantly on
our tongue have the capacity to produce
these odorous sulfur compounds through
putrefaction of
sulfur-containing proteins
okay so what can we do about it
many have concentrated on trying to
reduce the bacterial load in the mouth
with like antiseptic mouthwashes or
finding ways to trap the vscs
mechanically you can disrupt the biofilm
of bacteria on the tongue like with
various tongue scraping techniques
though tongue cleaning seems to work
more through reducing the substrates for
putrefaction rather than the bacteria
themselves
okay but if the substrates for vsc
production are the sulfur-containing
amino acids
and the sulfur-containing amino acids
are derived mainly from animal protein
meat and dairy what about using a
dietary approach
the vscs from animal protein may
actually explain why carnivore poop
smells so much different than herbivore
poop
and indeed eliminating the amount of
consumed proteins may significantly
reduce fitor x or a from the latin
meaning stench mouth
the reason they add fats and alcohol is
that they can both cause relaxation of
the lower esophageal sphincter
normally the only time you exhale odors
from your stomach is when you burp
because the sphincter at the top of the
stomach prevents stuff from backing up
but alcohol or a fat rich diet increases
the relaxation of that sphincter which
further increases the risk and severity
of bad breath
but most cases of halitosis occur due to
the decay of food residues in the mouth
by the bacteria that decompose proteins
and amino acids and produces the
volatile sulfur compounds so the
treatment of oral halitosis should
involve not just professional advice on
oral hygiene but also diet
dairy proteins for example are known to
break down in the mouth leading to the
release of amino acids that are rich in
sulfur dairy products are rich sources
of the milk protein casein and casein is
rich in the sulfur-containing amino acid
cysteine
which is a precursor to the formation of
the rotten egg gas hydrogen sulfide in
the oral cavity in fact that's how you
can test people for bad breath
cysteine challenge testing just have
people swish their mouth with it
when cysteine is degraded not only do
you get the hydrogen sulfide which
comprises a large part of the bad breath
bouquet
but you get sulfhydryl anions that fever
the growth of the very bacteria within
the mouth responsible for the protein
putrefaction that's central to the
production of oral mall loader in the
first place and
to the development of gum disease
so it's not just a one-two punch but a
triple threat
bad breath isn't just some aesthetic
issue these volatile sulfur compounds
can be toxic to the gums even at
extremely low concentrations
hydrogen sulfide reacts with collagen
and can alter the protein structure
thereby rendering your gums and jaw more
susceptible
to destruction
then you can develop these pockets of
putrid pus that can lead to more
halitosis
the periodontal pockets are the second
main source of the volatile sulfur
compounds even people with mild
periodontitis may have twice the risk of
reporting bad breath
finally let me touch on the role diet
has in so-called extraoral halitosis bad
breath that doesn't originate in the
mouth there are lots of drugs that can
do it including dietary supplements like
fish oil but there's another way people
can smell fishy
trimethylamine
trimethylamine urea is one of the
largest causes for undiagnosed body odor
it's when you can't sufficiently
metabolize a malodorous compound called
trimethylamine which is formed in your
gut when you eat lots of choline
the textbook presentation is urine
breath sweat and reproductive fluid
smelling like rotten or decaying fish
but what many doctors don't realize is
that the fish odor presentation may only
occur in like 10 percent of individuals
who have this predisposition
yes at high concentrations
trimethylamine has a you know foul
rotten fish odor but at low
concentrations it can just give you kind
of an
unpleasant garbage like breath
and because there are so many foods that
are rich in choline like the fact that
there are eggs found in so many foods
you may not make the connection between
your diet and your body odor
but you can always try cutting out foods
like egg yolks for a few weeks and see
if you smell any better
[Music]
you